SAI PRASHANTH CHANDRAMOULI ("SAI")

Seattle, WA | 480-703-5615 | saiprash1993@yahoo.co.in | in.linkedin.com/in/saipc | github.com/TDA

SUMMARY

Senior Software Development Engineer at Meta with 8+ years of experience building secure billion-user-scale web applications with React, Hacklang, Ruby on Rails, SDKs for the Android platform with Kotlin, backend services with Java, and serverless applications using AWS technologies. Ex-Bar Raiser at Amazon with over 450 interviews. Speaker and workshop host at 25+ Amazon and Meta-internal and external conferences.

EXPERIENCE

Meta, Senior Software Development Engineer, Responsibility & Privacy.

2021 - Present

- Launched WAIST 3.0 an industry leading algorithmic-transparency tool to explain how Meta's machine learning models contribute to the ads people see, with coverage in major tech media (Meta Launch news, Verge, Engadget, TechCrunch, US Today News).
- Launched Creative Intelligence Center for advertisers on Meta's Ads Manager, a first-of-its-kind ML explainability tool to gauge Video creative performance, extracting insights that lead to higher conversion rates, generating \$12M in revenue in H2 2023, projected to generate \$100M+ in FY2024.
- Served as **Tech-lead** for the Special Ads Framework (SAFR) team that oversees the validation and enforcement of regulatory constraints on Special Ads (Housing, Employment, Credit, Elections), leading a **team of 2 product engineers**.
- **Tech-lead** for the Ads ML Explainability team working on a product called WAIST ("why am I seeing this ad?") working on experimenting and adding transparency surfaces to Facebook and Instagram, **leading a team of 3 product engineers**.

Amazon, Software Development Engineer II, Alexa Runtime.

2020 - 2021

- Co-creator and lead designer of the SDK and Device software for a **new Alexa technology (patented)** that allows Alexa to be integrated with Android platform with minimal effort, reducing the engineering effort from **8 weeks to 0.2 days (99% reduction** in time consumed). Launching with <u>leading US</u> telecom provider enabling a revenue stream of **\$27.6 million**.
- Currently leading a **team of 3 engineers** designing the extension of the above technology to other platforms (iOS, Web) which will enable an additional incremental revenue stream of **\$24 million** pending approval from launch partner.
- · Led a **team of 3 engineers** to scale **2 Tier-1 services** (Amazon business critical services) to support **23,000 TPS** and perform Chaos/Resiliency testing to update Infrastructure setup, resulting in **zero** High-Severity events and **100% availability** for Christmas 2020.
- Lead engineer who implemented the On-the-Go initiative and **Skill Resumption** feature for Alexa (announced at Alexa Live 2020 and covered by leading tech magazines like <u>Techcrunch</u>), launching 6 new Alexa powered products (earphones, glasses, microwave, etc.) in 2020 and enabling a revenue stream of **\$6.2 million** for Amazon.
- Served as a **Bar Raiser at Amazon**, conducting **450+ interviews** and **leading debriefs** and **driving consensus** for hiring decisions across a multitude of roles, including Software Developers, Front-end Engineers, Product Managers, Data Scientists for Amazon, resulting in **116** successful hires.

Amazon, Software Development Engineer II, Compliance - Transaction Risk Management.

2017 - 2019

- Designed and implemented both the front-end and back-end for a **Self Service portal for non-engineers** (TPM's, Product and Compliance Managers) to automatically generate the code for **launching risk investigation** tools in different regions and marketplaces, reducing the engineering effort from **3** weeks to **0.5** days (96% reduction in time) for each new region, resulting in **3-year annualized savings** of \$350,000.
- Lead a **team of 4 engineers** through requirements, design and implementation phases for the Brexit-Compliance project, working with a cross-functional team of UX designers, Product managers and Compliance officers from London and Luxembourg to achieve the changes needed for Amazon to be compliant with Brexit.
- · Implemented and launched risk investigation tools in **3 new regions** Amazon Payments **UK**, **Europe**, and **India** enabling **18 types** of investigations for Amazon businesses to stay compliant with regulations.
- Designed and implemented clustered case support for investigating related merchants enabling investigations of up to **2800 sellers simultaneously** to be conducted and filed to regulatory bodies, resulting in a **savings of \$12,000** per year.
- Migrated legacy search service to AWS ElasticSearch reducing page load times from 8 seconds to 3.4 seconds (57% reduction) and reducing hardware cost by \$6500 a year (70% reduction in cost).

Amazon, Software Development Engineer, Compliance - Suspicious Activity Monitoring.

2016 – 2017

- Designed and implemented a pre-push hook to verify code before merging with live pipelines that reduced pipeline failures from **24 failures** a month to **11 failures** (**54% reduction** in failures) a month.
- · Implemented and launched support for Suspicious Activity monitoring, Denied Party Screening, Identity verification and TIN verification.
- . Designed and implemented a **Bulk report generation and download** feature, reducing investigation time from **9 hours** to **under 6 minutes** (**98% reduction** in time consumed) resulting in cost savings of **\$30,000** per year.
- · Received "Truth Seeker" award for actively working to reduce operational cost of software.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Technologies: HTML, CSS, JavaScript (ReactJS, jQuery), Ruby on Rails, Java, Kotlin, Android development.

AWS Technologies: Lambda, API Gateway, Amplify, AppSync, Cognito, DynamoDB, ElasticSearch, SQS, SNS, Network Load Balancer.

SPEAKING ENGAGEMENTS

Presented talks on the following topics to a combined total of 2300+ Amazon developers:

Webdevcon - Amazon's front-end engineering conference. Edinburgh, Seattle, Amsterdam, New York, Virtual.

2018 - 2021

- · Using Functional Programming with Java and JavaScript to reduce operational burden.
- . Data modeling for **DynamoDB / NoSQL** to support high read loads.
- Deno JS Usage at Amazon as a replacement for Node.js.
- · Using **React hooks** in production at Amazon focusing on Operational readiness.
- . Introductory talk on using React hooks to promote adoption of Hooks across Amazon.
- · Using CSS Grids in production to re-architect the Alexa web-app skill page.

· React Native with AWS toolchain for secure deployment in production for Amazon's external facing products.

Zoncon - Amazon's premier security conference.

2018

· Presented a talk to 1200 engineers on E-Mail header injections and how to prevent it in Amazon systems.

WORKSHOPS

Conducted the following workshops to a combined total of **800+** Amazon developers:

Webdevcon - Amazon's front-end engineering conference. London, Amsterdam, New York, Virtual.

2018 - 2021

- Creating and maintaining Component libraries for React based projects.
- Using **React Native with Electron** to create multi-platform applications from a single code-base.
- · Building ReactNative Mobile apps with AWS Amplify.
- · Building Serverless Applications with AWS.
- · Using **GraphQL** to build production services at Amazon.
- Building Serverless Web Applications with Native AWS.

EDUCATION

Arizona State University, Master's (Thesis) in Computer Science - Web Security.

May 2016

Anna University, India, Bachelor's in Computer Science and Engineering.

Mar 2014